Eric Ekholm

eric.ekholm@gmail.com · Website · Github · LinkedIn

I am a data scientist with over 5 years of experience using data to improve educational practice and decision making. I have handson experience in research design, machine learning, software engineering, and cloud computing. I am particularly passionate about communicating the results of my work in accessible language and intuitive visualizations.

Work Experience

Data Specialist 2021-Present

Chesterfield County Public Schools, Midlothian, VA

- Built dashboards displaying student assessment performance accessed by hundreds of users, using R, Shiny, Docker, and Google Cloud.
- Evaluated the return on investment of over \$5 million in new and existing programs using quantitative and qualitative methods.
- Developed and maintained several internal R packages used by the entire Research and Evaluation team.
- Developed and maintained ETL pipelines for integrating data from vendors into internal databases, using R, Go, and SQL Server.
- Fit an early warning model predicting student chronic absenteeism using R and the tidymodels framework. Educated division leaders on appropriate use of this model.
- Created and maintained an internal website containing all reports written by the Research and Evaluation team, using Quarto, Python, and Google Cloud.
- Led the migration of analytics tools from locally-hosted tools to Google Cloud tools, improving team efficiency.

Associate Director, Early Childhood Data

2019-2021

Virginia Department of Education, Richmond, VA

- Oversaw the development of LinkB5, a data portal used by thousands of early childhood programs across Virginia.
- Led data sharing and research efforts with external partners, including public and private organizations.
- Created hundreds of individualized early childhood reports and visuals for state legislators, using R and Rmarkdown.
- Combined data from public and internal sources to develop a model estimating the proportion of eligible children served by Virginia's early childhood programs. This model was used as part of a successful effort to appropriate millions in additional funding for early childhood programs.

Graduate Research Assistant 2016-2019

Virginia Commonwealth University School of Education, Richmond, VA

- Published 11 peer-reviewed articles on a variety of topics in education and quantitative methodology.
- Led statistical modeling and data management for the Motivation in Context lab.

Education

Ph.D, Educational Psychology

2016-2019

2011-2012

Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, VA

M.T., Education

Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, VA

B.A., English

2006-2010

Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA

Technologies and Languages

Languages: R, Python, SQL, Go, Julia, Bash

Technologies: Git, Quarto, Relational databases, NoSQL databases, Google Cloud Platform, Docker, GCP Vertex AI **Other:** Machine learning, Causal inference, Statistics, Data visualization, Research design, AI, Web development

Projects

Brain: A public notes site containing notes on statistics, data science, coding, and more.

Blueycolors: An R package that provides Bluey-inspired color palettes and ggplot2 scales. See the source on Github